EEPAK KUMAR

J +91-9801913391

✓ deepak.kumar3112@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/deepak-bits | github.com/deepak-bits

Objective

Freelance developer having 2+ years of experience with extensive background in various programming languages, developing applications and websites from the ground up. Specializes in Java, SpringBoot and JavaScript. Experience in writing highly readable and easily maintainable source code. Proven strengths in problem-solving and effective communication.

Technical Skills

Languages: Java, JavaScript, HTML/CSS, MySQL

Technologies/Frameworks: Spring Boot, React, Bootstrap Others: REST APIs, Data Structures, Algorithms, Git, OOPS

Experience

Freelance Web Developer

Jan 2021 - Present

- 2 years of freelance experience specializing in Java Spring Boot, delivering successful projects across diverse industries.
- Proven track record in designing, developing, and integrating scalable RESTful APIs using Java Spring Boot for efficient communication between software components.
- Proficient in utilizing Spring Data to manage and optimize databases, including ORM mapping, writing complex queries, and ensuring data integrity.
- Proficient in building responsive and user-friendly interfaces using HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, along with expertise in utilizing React for creating interactive web applications.
- Cross-functional collaboration and also experienced in working collaboratively with frontend and design teams, effectively integrating backend functionality with frontend components to deliver seamless user experiences.

Chegg India Pvt. Ltd.

Feb 2021 - Present

Junior Developer

Remote(Freelance)

- Learned to debug code fast and quick, built and designed APIs according to project's requirements.
 - Gained experience in writing code that follows object-oriented design principles along with S.O.L.I.D principles.

Projects

Library Management System | GitHub Link | Java, SpringBoot, MySQL, JPA/Hibernate

- A dynamic Spring Application that simplifies library book transactions for students with 7 APIs to add, get or update student details, books, author etc.
- Utilized Hibernate ORM for efficient data management and integrated with MySQL database for data persistence and DTOs to ensure privacy.
- Features include automatic card issuance, streamlined book issuing, returning and transaction recording.
- Added a mailing feature to the system enabling users to receive e-mail notifications for book issuance updates using spring's e-mail integration.
- Integrated Swagger for documenting APIs and providing an interactive user experience.

Ecommerce Application | GitHub Link | Java, SpringBoot, MySQL, JPA/Hibernate

- An online shopping application consisting around 10 APIs for creation, addition, updation and deletion of sellers, products, customers, cart and card.
- Utilized Hibernate ORM for database connection to MySQL and DTOs to ensure privacy.
- Enables user to add their card details, add items to cart and eventually checkout.
- Enables customer to fetch product list by specifying category or price along with the category.
- Used Spring's email integration that enables users to get order confirmation, shipping updates and Swagger for API documentation.
- Implemented custom exception class to provide clear and informative error messages to clients.

Education

Birla Institute of Technology and Science – Pilani

Aug. 2008 – May 2012

M.Sc.(Tech) Information Systems

GPA: 6.38 April 2008

D.A.V. Public School - XIIth CBSE Board

Percentage: 89.8

D.A.V. Public School - Xth

April 2006

CBSE Board

Percentage: 94.6